Good afternoon. So today's דף *daf* is ט"ו *tet-vav*. With today's דף
*daf*, we will, G-d willing, finish the first פרק *perek*. Not the
first פרק *perek*, the first משנה mishna, *mishna*. And as I said,
it's quite
interesting, this whole מסכת *masechet* is about 34 דף *daf* or something,
and just the first משנה mishna *mishna*, literally just the first משנה
mishna. *mishna* covers about half of the מסכת *masechet*. So, but we
will soon be turning, starting with the next משנה *mishna*, onto areas
a little bit more, that feel a little bit more contemporary. Anyway,
with today's דף *daf*, we finish the issues around the year, the
years for תרומות ומעשרות Trumos uMa'asros *terumot uma'asrot* and for שביעית Shevi'is.
*shvi'it*, and the difference between the various things. Grains, we were told,
grains and olives is a שליש *shalish*.
Fruit is חנטה Chanatah *chanatah*, the
blossoming. Vegetables are picking. The legumes are השרשה hashrasha. *hashrashah*, are inrooting.
By the way, I should say that Dov Luria pointed out yesterday
that תוספות Tosafos. *Tosfot* says that the issue of the vegetables by
picking is really, he says it's equivalent to גמר פרי gmar pri
*g'mar peri*, when the fruit is finished developing. It's just that you
pick it soon after it finished developing. And there's one opinion by
the legumes also that's גמר פרי gmar pri *g'mar peri*. I, as
I look, continue to look at that תוספות Tosafos. *Tosfot* and the
תוספות Tosafos *Tosfot* on the next דף *daf* that says the same
thing, תוספות *Tosfot* seems to really mean it,
like that if you had a גמר פרי gmar pri *g'mar peri*
in one year and the picking in the following year, if they
actually were separated, that you actually would go by גמר פרי gmar
pri. *g'mar peri* by the vegetables, not by לקיטה Lekitah *lakitah*, although
all of the evidence seems to say picked before ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah, *Rosh Hashanah*, picked after ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashanah*. Anyway,
תוספות *Tosfot* is trying to resolve other prices issues, wants to reframe
that as גמר פרי gmar pri, *g'mar peri*. Anyway, those are the
different types of things. What we have been seeing particularly is that
we've been focusing on fruit, which is by, goes by blossoming. They
also, the way in which fruit is different is that it goes
by אחד בשבט *echad b'shvat* or ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat *tu b'shvat*,
בית שמאי *Beit Shammai*, בית הלל *Beit Hillel*. Why it should go
by that, תוספות *Tosfot* says because the assumption is that if it
blossoms before ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat, *tu b'shvat*, it's got all the
rain it needed from before, before the first of תשרי Tishrei. *tishrei*.
After ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat. *tu b'shvat*, it's getting the rain it
needed from this year. Again, to that question of where did it
get, it goes by the year from which it got the rain
that it needed. So that's the issue about trees. And we've seen
now, what our focus is now is about אתרוג esrog, *etrog* because
since an אתרוג esrog *etrog* grows and continues to grow,
at all times in the year, continues to benefit from the rain
at all times of the year, in some ways it is considered
to be like a vegetable, specifically in terms of that when it,
that the year of which you take the תרומה Terumah ומעשרות *terumah
u'ma'asrot* is determined by the year in which it is picked. So
when it comes to issues about ערלה Orlah? *orlah*, when it comes
to issues about שמיטה Shmita *shemitah*, it goes by the blossoming, it
does not go by the year it's picked. When it comes to
the issue about which year you take מעשר Ma'aser *ma'aser* for, it
goes by the year that it is picked. Just to make things
a little bit more complicated, or less complicated, I don't know, is
it goes by the year it's picked, but remember we had the
story with רבי עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* who picked the אתרוג esrog. *etrog*
after אחד בשבט *echad b'shvat* before ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat. *tu b'shvat*
and he did with it like בית הלל *Beit Hillel*, בית שמאי
*Beit Shammai*, was playing safe, and that got a whole discussion in
the גמרא Gemara *gemara*. So you see from there that even though
you're going by when it's picked, which is a vegetable thing, by
the date of the calendar you're looking at the שבט Shevat. *shvat*
date. You're not looking at the תשרי Tishrei, *tishrei* date, right? You
notice that? So that's a very interesting hybrid. I mean, the אתרוג
esrog *etrog* is a hybrid as well, but even in the area
of תרומות ומעשרות terumos umasros, *terumot uma'asrot* where you treat it like
a vegetable and you go by where it's picked, the date you
look at is the ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat. *tu b'shvat* date. Just
to keep you nice and confused. Okay, so that's what the גמרא
Gemara *gemara* is going to sort of turn to now. Let's just
get a little bit, a little further so everybody gets a little
grounded. So it says like this, we're
at the bottommost,
we're at the bottom of י"ד עמוד ב' *yud-dalet amud-bet*, אמר רבה
Rabba, בר רב הונא *amar Rabba bar Rav Huna*. So it's about
10 lines from the bottom, line starts towards בא *ba*, second בא
*ba*. Okay. אמר רבה בר רב הונא השתא דאמר רבן גמליאל De'amar
Rabban Gamliel אתרוג esrog אחר לקיטה Lekitah. *amar Rabba bar Rav Huna
hashta d'amar Rabban Gamliel etrog achar lakitah*. So now that רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel. *Rabban Gamliel*, this was actually a debate of רבן גמליאל
Rabban Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* and רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* says it's like a tree in all respects, רבן גמליאל Rabban
Gamliel *Rabban Gamliel* said no, for מעשרות *ma'asrot* it's like a vegetable
and goes by when it's picked. Now that רבן גמליאל *Rabban Gamliel*
says that an אתרוג esrog *etrog* goes by when it's picked, איסורו
כירק keyerek? *issuro k'yerek*. So you're treating it for מעשר Ma'aser *ma'aser*
like a vegetable, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah שלו תשרי Tishrei *Rosh Hashanah
shelo tishrei*. So against what we said before in the whole רבי
עקיבא *Rabbi Akiva* story, he is saying, let's be consistent. If we
go by when it's picked, we should go by תשרי Tishrei *tishrei*,
like a real vegetable.
מיתבי *metivei*, they challenge on this, that's not what it says in
the
ברייתא Braita. *braita*. רבי שמעון אלעזר אומר ליקט אתרוג esrog, ערב ט"ו
בשבט Tu B'Shevat עד שלא תבא החמה וחזר וליקט משתבא החמה אין
תורמין ומעשרין מזה על זה *Rabbi Shimon Elazar omer likat etrog erev
tu b'shvat ad shelo tavo
hachamah v'chazar v'likat mishetavo hachamah ein tormin u'ma'asrin mizeh al zeh*. You
don't take
תרומה
ומעשרין *terumah u'ma'asrin* from
this on that. Okay, so anyway it's clear two things: you go
by picking and you go by ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shevat, Now just
to give another scenario, that's like in the middle of a שמיטה
Shmita year between years one and two or you know or four
and five where the only difference is is it old or is
it new. But there's other times in where it actually changes what
type of מעשר Ma'aser you're taking. מעשר שלישית נכנסת לרביעית, Ma'aser Shlishis
nichneses lirviis, if it was year three in the שמיטה Shmita, cycle
going into year four. So in year three you take מעשר עני
Ma'aser Ani and in year four you take מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni.
So שלישית מעשר ראשון ומעשר עני, shlishis Ma'aser Rishon uMa'aser Ani, so
the stuff you picked from before ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat was you
take מעשר ראשון Ma'aser Rishon and מעשר עני. Ma'aser Ani. רביעית reviis
and the fourth year, מעשר ראשון ומעשר שני, Ma'aser Rishon uMa'aser Sheni,
after ט"ו בשבט, Tu B'Shevat you're also it's a different מעשר Ma'aser
you're going to take: you're going to take מעשר שני. Ma'aser Sheni.
So in addition to being a נפקא מינא nafka mina that you
can't take from the old to the new, it's also a question
of which מעשר Ma'aser you are taking. And just to make it
clear, you know again because this is so חזר, chazar, right, here
is ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, okay, this
was here all your various ראש השנה'ס. Rosh Hashanahs. So back here
was שמיטה, Shmita okay, then you got ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah, in
year one of the cycle, now you're year two in the cycle,
now you're this is you know your third year of the cycle,
right, this is your fourth year of the cycle. Okay, so here
like שמיטה Shmita was before, was before we got started. So here
you're taking מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, מעשר שני, Ma'aser Sheni, here you're
taking מעשר עני, Ma'aser Ani, and here you're taking מעשר שני. Ma'aser
Sheni. Now when did you pick? You picked this thing, this אתרוג,
esrog not at ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah but way here at ט"ו
בשבט. Tu B'Shevat
Okay, you're picking this אתרוג Etrog, at ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shevat. Let
me draw a nice אתרוג. Etrog, That looks like an apple. But
anyway, whatever, okay, it's
got a bunch of bumps.
Okay, you picked this אתרוג Etrog right before ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shevat
Okay, even though you picked it four months after ראש השנה, Rosh
Hashanah תשרי-טבת, Tishrei-Teves, okay,
you picked it four months after after ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, you
were still going to be taking and everybody else in everything that's
growing this year, all the grain that's ripening this year, all the
you know everything else, you know all the vegetables that are being
picked, everything that's happening this year you're taking מעשר עני, Ma'aser Ani,
this אתרוג Etrog that was picked before ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat. you're
taking מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni based on your year three, right? It's
only after ט"ו בשבט, Tu B'Shevat. only once you get from like
a third into the year that you are finally beginning to take
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni which is the מעשר Ma'aser of this year.
Okay, so that's how the ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat matters. Now by
other fruit, that's really true by all fruit, by other fruit it
would be that if it blossoms before ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat then
it's מעשר עני, Ma'aser Ani, by the אתרוג Etrog it goes by
if it's picked. And just by the way to just finish that
you appreciate the irony, let's say it's not an אתרוג, Etrog let's
say I don't know what it is, it's a
peach or a lemon or whatever. If it blossoms here, right, let's
say you actually pick it here. You're going to pick a peach,
right, at the end of year four and you're going to take
מעשר עני. Ma'aser Ani. You understand? Right, this is a מעשר שני
Ma'aser Sheni year but it blossomed before
ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat and picking means nothing by fruit. But when
you actually come to eat it, because you're not taking תרומות ומעשרות
terumos umasros. here, when you actually are ready to eat it at
the end of year four you're taking מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani because
it blossomed before ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shevat. Okay, so it's very it's
very complicated. By אתרוג Etrog in a way it's a little easier
because you go it goes by right before you're about to eat
it. But even so, even though you pick it even though you're
picking it here a third into the year you're still taking מעשר
עני, Ma'aser Ani, yes.
Yeah, so move three years ahead to the seventh year. Yeah, you
would actually be picking fruit on שמיטה Shmita?
and taking from right, exactly.
Taking tithes on during the שמיטה?
Shmita And we're going to get to that later in the תוספות.
Well, right, we're going to get to that later in the תוספות.
Just totally back to basics. Where does not even this. מעשר ראשון
Ma'aser Rishon goes where? מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni goes where? מעשר עני
Ma'aser Ani goes where?
Okay, מעשר ראשון Ma'aser Rishon goes I
don't mean a where who gets it? לוי. Levi.
מעשר שני Ma'aser Sheni is ירושלים. Yerushalayim. And מעשר עני Ma'aser Ani
goes to עניים. Aniyim. Okay, great.
And then after all that's done תרומה goes to a כהן. Kohen.
Yeah. But before, before all of that.
Okay, and ביכורים Bikkurim comes before everything. Ah,
and then how does this affect ערלה?
Orlah Ah,
well the ערלה Orlah goes by no, ערלה Orlah. is based on
how many years it's since it's been planted not based on the
שמיטה Shmita cycle. But it's the same issue when it hits ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah, the first ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah. after it's been
planted, that's the end of year one, but it only is considered
to go into year four after the ט"ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat. after
it's been planted. So if we don't assume a שמיטה Shmita cycle
we assume anywhere in the
year and we're... Here's where you plant the tree. This is my
terrible tree for everybody to see, not a lollipop. Here's where you
plant your tree, okay? So here's the first ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah,
the next ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah, the next ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah
So here it's in—after it hits ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah. now it's
in year two. Hits next ראש השנה, Rosh Hashanah. it's in year
three. But it's not רבעי Reva'i because you have to go to
ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shevat.
But doesn't that depend on how close to ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah
you planted it, whether there's thirty days before?
Yeah, right. Exactly.
It's gotta be a year.
Right, it's gotta be a year. But that's the ערלה. Orlah ערלה
is not based on this cycle; that's based on from the time
it's regarded.
And then
you start eating it, so that's next ראש השנה. Rosh Hashanah This
is four. And then you have to wait, you have to wait
till ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'shvat The ט"ו בשבט Tu B'shvat. here, then
it's—this is נטע רבעי Neta Reva'i and then you can eat it.
Of the fifth year, right?
After ט"ו בשבט Tu B'shvat,
of the fifth year.
רבא Rabba goes by...
What? רבא Rabba goes by—yeah, well, at the beginning and ט"ו בשבט
Tu B'shvat, at the end.
Yeah, but we had that—why would you use that?
Can we get—can we move on? Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, now anyway, you see there that you go by
picking, and you see you go by ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'shvat, So
the גמרא Gemara says top of ט"ו עמוד א', Tes Vav Amud
Aleph, מאן שמיע ליה דאזיל בתר לקיטה? Man shemi'a lei de'azil batar
lekita? Who do we know goes by picking? רבן גמליאל. רבן גמליאל
holds it. I mean, anyway, the point is it's going by picking,
that ברייתא. Braita. וקתני, Vekatani, and it says שבט. Shevat So you
see it has that you go by picking and it goes by
ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'shvat, That was explicit in the ברייתא. braisa, So
yeah, it is a hybrid. אלא אי מהא הכי, Ela i meihachi,
fine. If the statement was said by רבא בר רב הונא, Rabba
Bar Rav Huna, this is the way it was said. אמר רבא
בר רב הונא, Amar Rabba Bar Rav Huna, אף על גב Af
al gav דאמר רבן גמליאל אתרוג אחר לקיטה כירק, Etrog achar lekita
keyerek, although רבן גמליאל says it goes by picking like a vegetable,
ראש השנה שלו שבט, Rosh Hashanah shelo Shevat, it still is going
to be—we're going to use שבט Shevat. as the ראש השנה. Rosh
Hashanah? So as opposed to רבא בר רב הונא's Rabba Bar Rav
Huna's original version of the statement which seemed to want to make
it consistent, the evidence is that it's not consistent; it's a hybrid.
So now we're rephrasing his statement to acknowledge that it's a hybrid,
that yes, you go by picking by the אתרוג, Etrog but nevertheless
because it's a tree, you're still going to go by ט"ו בשבט.
Tu B'shvat, Okay, now the גמרא Gemara says
a little parenthetical comment, מאי שנא התם דקתני האי שנייה נכנסת לשלישית?
Mai shna hatam de'ktani hai shniya nichneset lishlishit? Normally when we give
an example about how the thing will differ when it goes from
one year to the next, based on what מעשר Ma'aser you take,
it's the example is the second year going into the third. Like
when it spoke about picking the vegetables, it says you picked vegetables
right before ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah of the second year and then
right after ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah and it became the third year.
So why there do we normally give an example of second year
going into the
third, ומאי שנא הכא דקתני האי שלישית נכנסת לרביעית? umai shna hacha
de'katni hai shlishit nichneset lirevi'it? And when we give the example about
the אתרוג, Etrog, we talk about it being the third year entering
into the fourth. I mean, it's all just an example of where
the מעשר Ma'aser, changes, but why do we change the example? So
the גמרא Gemara. says מלתא אגב אורחיה קמשמע לן, Milta agav orchia
kamashma lan, it's teaching us something in
passing, דאתרוג קשי ליה ידא, De'etrog kashi lei yada, that an אתרוג
esrog, tree is like—the handling is difficult for it. ואיידי דממשמשי ביה
כולי עלמא בשביעית, Ve'aidi demamshmushi bei kulei alma beshvi'it, and since the
trees are not protected in שמיטה Shmita, and everybody is going and
grabbing fruit off of the tree, לא טעין פירא עד תלת שנין,
Lo ta'in pira ad telat shanin, it's going to take three years
until the fruit starts coming again. Now if that was really true,
it would be a disaster every year, because you'd lose like three
years of growth. But it basically is saying over here during שמיטה,
Shmita? everybody is grabbing the fruit off of the tree, and it's
not going to start regrowing fruit until somewhere here, so it's fit
to be picked already in the fourth year. It's going to take
it into the third year to start regrowing fruit. So other cases
we could talk about second year going into the third, but this
אתרוג esrog tree, there's not going to be any fruit second going
into the third. It's only going to be fruit to pick going
into the fourth. If that were really true, it would be a
disaster to own an אתרוג esrog. tree in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael
because that means you're only getting products like three out of every
seven years.
Is the גמרא Gemara saying that the אתרוג esrog tree is different
than all other trees or everybody runs and picks stuff off of
trees during שמיטה?
Shemittah Everybody picks stuff off of trees. The question is how much
is the growth of
the tree impacted through that handling? Now maybe it's true by other
trees as well, we're just not giving the example by others. But
anyway, it is saying that the אתרוג esrog is delicate and it's
hurt by this type of a handling. Now again, maybe it's not
saying always, but it's just saying often it will take for them
to fully recover will take into the third year, so we wanted
to give that as the
example.
And why is the אתרוג esrog singled out like as a ירק,
Yerek, כירק?
Because the fruit doesn't—other trees, the fruit blossoms, grows and sort of
falls off the tree and has to be picked that year. Whereas
an אתרוג, esrog the fruit stays on from year to year and
whenever the rain is coming, it always helps the growth of the
fruit.
So it's ירק-like Yerek in that
regard.
Exactly, exactly. Yeah.
One question is, do we ever say המציאות Hametziut has changed? Like
now 98% of אתרוגים Etrogim are used for סוכות Sukkot and then
thrown out. Do we say, okay,
well... take תרומות ומעשרות, terumos umasros? if you want to eat it
you take תרומות ומעשרות. terumos umasros, Because like you know the chances
of anyone using it other than the end consumer, no I'm not
the exporter, I'm selling you an אתרוג, esrog why should I have
to bother taking תרומות ומעשרות? terumos umasros.
All right, I'm not going to get into who the חיוב chiyuv
is on by the תרומות ומעשרות, terumos umasros but you know but
there is a general חיוב chiyuv that
even before you sell it you're חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. terumos
umasros So anyway, but like
you know if I'm gathering wood, I don't have to take תרומות
ומעשרות terumos umasros, on it,
because you're not חייב chayav in תרומות ומעשרות terumos umasros.
on wood or מים mayim or something.
Oh you're saying it's not פרי. pri. If you were to start
considering it not פרי pri you wouldn't be יוצא yotzei because the
תורה Torah calls it פרי עץ הדר pri eitz hadar and some
of the פסולים psulim of אתרוג Esrog. are based on the fact
that it's not ראוי לאכילה, rauy l'achila, it's not considered פרי. pri.
That would be a פסול psul of an אתרוג. esrog All right,
let's keep on going. בעי מיניה רב יוחנן מרבי ינאי, Ba'ei minei
Rav Yochanan mei-Rabbi Yannai, רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan asked of רבי ינאי,
Rabbi Yannai, אתרוג ראש השנה שלו אימתי? esrog rosh hashanah shelo eimasai?
When's the ראש השנה? Rosh Hashanah, Presumably he had the same question
which is if you go by picking, maybe it should be תשרי.
Tishrei, אמר ליה שבט, Amar lei Shevat, he said to him שבט.
Shevat. I mean it's a good logic תשרי, but we see in
the ברייתא, in the תנאי tannaic evidence, that even an אתרוג esrog
you go by שבט. Shevat, So he said שבט, Shevat so then
he said back to him, שבט דחדשים או שבט דתקופה? Shevat dechodashim
o Shevat detkufah? Do we mean שבט Shevat, of the month, the
month that's called שבט, Shevat or do we mean שבט Shevat of
the season? What does it mean of the season? So
there's something called תקופת טבת, tkufas Teves, right? Because the seasons are
divided based on the month that begins them, so תקופת תשרי tkufas
Tishrei is the fall, תקופת טבת tkufas Teves is the what? Winter.
תקופת ניסן tkufas Nissan is the spring and תקופת תמוז tkufas Tammuz
is the summer. So תקופת שבט tkufas Shevat really רש״י Rashi says
means a month into the winter. Okay, so
since תקופת... tkufas... so what? No, it's תקופת טבת tkufas Teves but
it means do we go by the month called שבט or do
we look at the seasons and say a month into the winter?
Okay, this is when the lunar and the solar year are out
of whack, so maybe we should go by a month into the
winter. Now it's a bizarre question, right? You could ask that on
the whole משנה, every time the משנה said ט״ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat
or תשרי or whatever, say you know do we mean when it
says ראש חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh Tishrei for all the other תרומות
ומעשרות, terumos umasros maybe we mean the fall, maybe we don't mean
ראש חודש תשרי. Rosh Chodesh Tishrei. Maybe he's asking this specifically by
אתרוג esrog because since אתרוג etrog, is so bizarre and has such
a like a tailor-made status, maybe here too there's a you know
even there's not such a logic to go by ט״ו בשבט, Tu
B'Shevat, maybe somehow it makes more sense to focus on seasons rather
than months.
But he's asking same, the date would be the same date.
What are you talking about? No it wouldn't. When I... you're telling
me every ראש חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh Tishrei comes out when the
fall begins? Depends on how the lunar and solar year are in
sync that year. The season is based on the solar year. Right,
okay. So he says what are we talking about? Months or seasons?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he said back to him, or... אמר
ליה דחדשים, Amar lei dechodashim, fine. Okay, so תוספות says, if you
look at תוספות או שבט דתקופה, Tosafos o Shevat detkufah, המתניתין נמי
דקתני באחד בשבט כבאי. hamatnisin nami diktani b'echad b'shvat k'v'ai. Okay, אף
על גב דלאו באתרוג. af al gav delav b'esrog. So he says
you could have asked it on the משנה. Again, it would be
bizarre, right? To ask it about ראש חודש תשרי Rosh Chodesh Tishrei
by other things by תרומות ומעשרות. Terumos U'Ma'aseros I think it was
specifically by אתרוג etrog just because אתרוג Esrog is so bizarre they
thought maybe this would be different as well. Anyway, the conclusion is
you go by the calendar date. Okay, continuing in the גמרא. Gemara
בעי מיניה רבא מרב נחמן, Ba'ei minei Rava mei-Rav Nachman, רבא Rava
asked of רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, ואמרי לה רבי יוחנן מרבי ינאי,
v'amrei lah Rabbi Yochanan mei-Rabbi Yannai, some say רב יוחנן Rav Yochanan
asked of רבי ינאי. Rabbi Yannai. הייתה שנה מעוברת מהו? Haysa shanah
m'uberess mahu? Let's say it was a leap year. So that means
again that the now maybe again it's a particular... like anytime it's
a leap year the ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah gets delayed a year,
you know but here the what? A month, not a year, right.
But I don't know, somehow again they're thinking I don't know why
it's specifically a question of ט״ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat because you know
the month gets added like somewhere here, right? So the fact that
it's a leap year the month gets added, right? That pushes off
you know this pushes off תשרי a month. So maybe you should
say that that's you know that the תרומות ומעשרות Terumos u-Ma’asros. go
by אלול, Elul, not by תשרי, right if it's being pushed off.
But maybe the logic is the following is that for the issue
of ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah we know it's going to go by
the date even if there were thirteen months here because that really
defines the next year. But ט״ו בשבט, Tu B'Shevat, which is not
like a mark off of a year, this is really a mark
off of a year, maybe again it's a little bit more seasonal
related and maybe it should shift based on whether it was a
leap year or not. But of course that's crazy because if it's
a leap year the whole point of doing a leap year is
to adjust the seasons. So it's ממה נפשך. mimah nafshach. If you
want to look at calendar date you should always go by ט״ו
בשבט. Tu B'Shevat. If you want to be sensitive to seasonal issues
then when it's a leap year it adjusts it was to address
the seasonal issues. So it's unclear what the גמרא Gemara thought the
question was. Let's and why it again asks it in this context
of ט״ו בשבט Tu B'Shevat and doesn't ask it and doesn't ask
it in general by the dates. But let's take a look. הייתה
שנה מעוברת מהו? Haysa shanah m'uberess mahu? אמר ליה הלך אחר רוב
שנים. Amar lei halach achar rov shanim. Yeah, you go by the
normal date that you go by normal years, you don't start making
things different because it's a leap year. Okay. אמר רבא Rava *Amar
Rava* אתרוג בשישית שנכנסה לשביעית *Esrog bashishis shenichnesa leshvi'is*. Now we're going
to have some fun. Okay, it was a sixth year אתרוג *Esrog*
that's going into the seventh year, פטור patur מן המעשר ופטור מן
הביעור *Patur min hamaser upatur min habiyur*. It's exempt from מעשר Ma'aser
*Maser* and exempt from ביעור Biur? *Biur*. ביעור Biur. *Biur* is a
reflection of its status of קדושת שביעית Kedushas Shevi'is. *Kedushas shvi'is*, which
means that it has to be eaten within a certain amount of
time. I'm just going to read it and then not only will
I unpack it, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* will unpack it. ובשביעית שנכנסה
לשמינית *Uvishvi'is shenichnesa lishminis*, a seventh year going into an eighth year
אתרוג *Esrog*, פטור במעשר Patar be'maiser. וחייב בביעור *Patur bemaser vechayav beviur*.
Ah yes, you picked it. פטור במעשר Patar be'maiser. וחייב בביעור *Patur
bemaser vechayav beviur* is exempt from מעשר Ma'aser. *Maser*
and obligated in ביעור Biur *Biur*.
So, let's take a look. So hold on one I just want
to check one thing.
One minute. Right,
so like we're assuming that we're talking here about about when you...
yeah, when you picked it... no, let's say when it goes
by חנטה Chanatah *Chanata*. So let's take a look here at the
scenario. Okay,
here you have ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah *Rosh Hashana*, ראש השנה Rosh
Hashanah *Rosh Hashana*, ראש השנה Rosh Hashanah.
*Rosh Hashana*. This is year six, this is year seven. Okay, so
here is your אתרוג *Esrog* and here is ט״ו בשבט *Tu B'Shvat*.
Okay.
Now, it was שישית שנכנסה לשביעית *Shishis shenichnesa leshvi'is*. Let me just
check one thing, hold on one sec.
Okay, right. חנטה Chanatah, *Chanata*, right.
And then you have seven going
into
eight.
So, okay. So what we have is the following. So we have
שביעית Shevi'is, נכנסה לשמינית *Shvi'is nichnesa lishminis*... לשביעית *Leshvi'is*, which means that
what that means is that it was picked here.
I'll draw my tree again. That's my tree, now I'm getting better
at drawing trees. Okay, it חנט *Chanat* here and it was, okay,
it חנט *Chanat* here and
it was picked here. All of this happened between the two ט״ו
בשבט *Tu B'Shvat*. That's the first
case: שישית שנכנסה לשביעית *Shishis shenichnesa leshvi'is*. מעשר Ma'aser. goes by
לקיטה lekita. in
an
אתרוג. So
you're making פשט Pshat of
שמיטה Shemittah for
this. Well, yeah, you
could have that scenario because it was
הפקר Hefker for
everybody. Well,
we'll get to that. Okay. So that's this scenario. So scenario number
one would be
would be that it's a six that it follows the laws of
it follows the laws for שמיטה Shemittah it's a sixth year fruit
and for מעשר Ma'aser it's a seventh, okay, which would mean what
would that mean? If you say it follows sixth year for שמיטה
Shemittah is there is there laws of ביעור? Biur. No, because it's
not a it's not a so no קדושת שביעית. Kedushas Shevi'is.
No קדושת שביעית. Kedushas Shevi'is. And for מעשר, Ma'aser well if it's
a seventh year fruit for מעשר Ma'aser do you take תרומות ומעשרות
in the seventh year? No. So that would mean no
מעשר. Ma'aser. That would be in that scenario. Now, now let's look
at scenario two. Scenario two is blossomed here and was picked here.
Okay. So in that case it is a seventh year for שמיטה
Shemittah for שמיטה Shemittah purposes and an eighth year for מעשר. Ma'aser
חייב Chayav in everything? So, seventh year for שמיטה Shemittah does it
have קדושה? Kedusha? It has קדושת שביעית. Kedushas Shevi'is, And eighth year
for מעשר Ma'aser it has it's חייב במעשר Chayav be'ma'aser right? This
is so weird. So, are we having fun yet? Yes. So let's
take a look.
Put that on the final, okay?
Let's take a look now. Wait wait wait. In the first scenario,
when is it picked? It's picked in the after ט"ו בשבט Tu
B'shvat. in the seventh year. It's picked during שביעית. Shevi'is? Yeah.
Was
always picked during שביעית, Shevi'is, but when during שביעית? Shevi'is Okay. Got
it.
Yes. You more or less have that? All right. Let's read that
again. Okay. So it says like this.
Let's try this again. Okay. אמר רבא אתרוג בת ששית שנכנסה לשביעית
פטורה מן המעשר ופטורה מן הביעור. Amar Rava: Esrog bat shishis shenichnesah
l'shevi'is, peturah min ha'ma'aser upeturah min ha'biur.
So it's exempt from מעשר Ma'aser and exempt from ביעור. Biur?
That worked, right? Okay, yeah. ובת שביעית שנכנסה לשמינית פטורה במעשר וחייבת
בביעור. U'vas shevi'is shenichnesah l'shminis, peturah be'ma'aser vechayeves be'biur.
So he has it חייבת בביעור, Chayaves Be'biur, קדושת שביעית, Kedushas Shevi'is.
but he has פטורה במעשר. Peturah be'maiser. That doesn't work. ביעור biur.
in this year? Okay, well yeah, yeah, it has קדושת שביעית. Kedushas
Shevi'is. It grew there. Okay, but remember our case? But he has
פטורה מן הביעור Petura min ha'biur so that's going to be the
problem.
פטורה מן המעשר.
Peturah min ha'maiser. Have everybody's completely confused or do you have it?
All right. All right. אמר ליה אביי בשלמא סיפא. Amar lei Abbaye:
Bishlama seifa. So אביי Abbaye is going to start by saying I
understand your second part of your statement where you say what do
you say by your second part? You say פטורה במעשר וחייבת בביעור,
Petura be'maiser vechayeves be'biur, לחומרא. L'chumra.
You're being strict. What does it mean you're לחומרא? L'chumra? It means
that, one minute.
Hold on, hold on.
No, what he means is you're being strict to consider it to
be a שמיטה Shemittah fruit. It starts by the חייבת בביעור. Chayaves
Be'biur. Once you're considering it to be a שמיטה Shemittah fruit, obviously
you're going to say פטורה במעשר. Peturah be'ma'aser. But I get the
idea that in terms of שמיטה Shemittah you're fundamentally starting by being
strict. אלא רישא פטורה מן הביעור אמאי? Ella reisha petura min ha'biur
amai? But okay, let's not get caught up in this. Let's look
at this this will clarify it. But the beginning part where you
say that it's exempt from ביעור. biur Why do you say it's
exempt from ביעור? biur? דאמינא זיל בתר חנטה. D'aminah zil basar chanatah.
Because you're going by the חנטה Chanatah and the חנטה chanatah happened
before ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'shvat? אי הכי תחייב במעשר. Ei hachi techayev
be'ma'aser.
If that's true that you go by חנטה, Chonata. why isn't it
חייב במעשר? Chayav be'ma'aser? Now again, the obvious answer is because מעשר
Ma'aser goes by לקיטה. lekita, But he's saying if you're going by
חנטה Chonata. here to say that it's not a שמיטה Shemittah fruit,
then that should determine אביי's Abbaye assumption is the שמיטה Shemittah determines
the מעשר. ma’aser So he says this I get, the שמיטה Shemitah
we ruled it has קדושת שביעית. Kedushas Shevi'is That'll determine the מעשר
ma’aser and that will say meaning we said it should be חייב
במעשר Chayav be'ma'aser but רבא's Rava statement, רבא Rava said it's פטור
במעשר. Patar be'maiser And that's being stricter? פטור במעשר. Patar be'maiser? It's
stricter because you start with מעשר ma’aser but שביעית, Shevi'is, that's אביי's
Abbaye understanding. Here you start with שביעית Shevi'is I get why you
say it's פטור במעשר patur be-ma’aser but here I get why there's
no קדושת שביעית Kedushas Shevi’is. but מעשר ma’aser should follow and מעשר
ma’aser. should be and therefore there should be חייב במעשר. Chayav be'ma'aser.
I don't get why you're saying okay so let's take a look.
So that's what he said. So he says why there are you
saying that it is that it is חייב במעשר? Chayav be'ma'aser? That
it is why do you say פטור במעשר? patur be-ma’aser Should be
חייב במעשר. Chayav be'ma'aser.
Because it was picked during שביעית, Shevi’is correct?
Yes. And that seems that's really what רבא's Rava answer is but
אביי Abbaye doesn't get it. אביי Abbaye assumes it should all follow
the שביעית Shevi’is. status. So that's what he says. אמאי דאמינא אזיל
בתר חנטה, Amai de-amina azil basar chanatah,
so you’re saying it’s... it’s פטור patur. in שביעית Shevi’is? because you
go by blossoming? אי הכי תתחייב במעשר, ei hachi titchayev be-ma’aser, so
מעשר ma’aser should follow שביעית. Shevi’is. So why are you saying that
it is also פטור במעשר patur be-ma’aser? in that scenario? What do
you mean follow שביעית?
Shevi’is Because you don’t take מעשר ma’aser in שביעית. Shevi’is Mean, no,
follow
its status.
Its status is no קדושת שביעית. Kedushas Shevi’is So since from שביעית
Shevi’is, it’s considered a sixth year, for מעשר ma’aser it should be
considered a sixth year. You can’t consider it a sixth year for
שביעית shviit. and a seventh year for מעשר ma’aser and have no
קדושת שביעית Kedushas Shevi’is. and no חיוב chiyuv of תרומות ומעשרות. That’s
אביי’s Abaye question. Logically that actually works, but he says, no, if
it’s sixth year for שביעית, shviit. then it’s going to be חייב
chayav in מעשר. ma’aser. That’s his question. Okay? So אמר ליה, amar
lei, so he said back an interesting... rather than saying a principled
thing like we were drawing on the board, that it could have
a double status, he says, I’m willing to agree with you that
you go by חנטה Chonata. consistently. But nevertheless, יד הכל ממשמשין בה
ואת אמרת תתחייב במעשר? yada kol memashmeshim ba v’at amart titchayev be-ma’aser?
He says, look, even if I concede that מעשר ma’aser logically should
follow the שמיטה Shemitah. status and it should be חייב במעשר, chayav
be-ma’aser, it should be a sixth year מעשר ma’aser fruit, but what
happens in... I’m sorry. No. I’m sorry. No. He’s going back to
this case, right? Yeah. You’re right, you’re right. This case he says,
you’re wrong אביי, Abaye, it does... מעשר ma’aser does not follow שמיטה.
Shemitah שמיטה Shemitah. goes by when it blossoms, so it’s no קדושת
שביעית. Kedushas Shevi’is, מעשר ma’aser goes when it’s picked and therefore no
מעשר. ma’aser Okay? Like we said. Your question was, why do I
say פטור במעשר patur be-ma’aser. here? Logically we should say yes קדושת
שביעית, Kedushas Shevi’is, blossomed in the seventh year. Yes חייב במעשר, chayav
be-ma’aser, picked in the eighth, right? So we set up here חייב
במעשר. chayav be-ma’aser. Why do I say פטור במעשר? patur be-ma’aser He
says, it’s obvious. If this was חייב במעשר chayav be-ma’aser when it
grew here, what’s going to be the reality of this tree? Everybody’s
going to be... it’s free access to everyone, right? People are going
to be going and picking it, right? So when you get over
here and you pick and you say am I חייב במעשר, chayav
be-ma’aser, even though it doesn’t have קדושת שביעית, Kedushas Shevi’is even though
it is an eighth year
fruit, right? An eighth year fruit and now it’s not הפקר, hefker,
now it’s a מעשר maaser. status that’s not הפקר. hefker. The reality
is that when it was
growing, I... you couldn’t stop people from accessing it. It was free
for all. And some type of a thing that is... everybody has
access to is something that is פטור במעשר. patur be-ma’aser Okay? So
therefore, so therefore it is possible here that it is because it’s
a... it has קדושת שביעית Kedushas Shevi’is here, it’s חייב בביעור, chayav
be-biur, right? So then even... so then therefore by the time you
get around to pick it, because it grew in the eighth year;
people had access in the seventh year, people had access to it
in the seventh year, you can't, you’re not going to be חייב
במעשר, chayav be-ma’aser, because it was fruit that was accessible to everyone.
So really, really what you’re saying is, what really his argument is,
in a way, it’s... it’s... אסורה אבל פטורה, asura aval patura, I
don’t know if that’s the right terminology. In other words, the... really
the חיוב chiyuv should be there except for an extenuating circumstance you
can’t prevent people from taking it during the שבי Shevi year. Right?
So we’re going to act as if it’s... it’s פטור. pattur But
you see what I’m saying?
Hold on a second.
It’s not that the conceptual basis for being חייב chayav is absent.
The conceptual basis for being חייב chayav is...
you know what, you know what, you know what? I’m sorry. I
just misexplained it. I was too much being led by the way
I wanted to sort of see how it worked. I apologize. Hold
on. I just misexplained it. רש"י Rashi says, the way רש"י Rashi
explains what’s going on here is... I’m sorry... is that רבא Rava
agrees to אביי Abaye that the... that the מעשר maaser. follows... follows
שמיטה. Shemitah. So here, in this case, where it has קדושת שביעית
Kedushas Shevi’is. because it grew here, so it is פטור במעשר patur
be-ma’aser? because that follows the fact that it had קדושת שביעית. Kedushas
Shevi’is, Okay. I’m sorry. So that’s the way רש"י Rashi says that
אביי... Abaye... רבא Rava agrees with אביי Abaye that the מעשר maaser
follows שמיטה. Shemitah. So that explains this, אביי Abaye was happy with
this. Once you say it has קדושת שביעית, Kedushas Shevi’is, it’s פטור
pattur במעשר b'maaser. that follows. Okay? Even though it was picked after,
etc. Here was
אביי’s Abaye question. If it is... if it doesn’t have קדושת שביעית,
Kedushas Shevi’is. how could it be פטור pattur במעשר? b'maaser Again, assuming
מעשר maaser. follows שמיטה. Shemitah. And here’s where רבא’s Rava answer was.
Look. It’s true it doesn’t have קדושת שביעית. Kedushas Shevi’is But there’s
a reality. The reality is is that you’re having אתרוג trees growing
in שמיטה. shmita You could be jumping up and down and telling
people, oh it doesn’t have קדושת שביעית Kedushas Shevi’is because it all
blossomed, you know, because it’s from the previous year, whatever. But the
reality is that people are going to be grabbing at it and
taking it anyway. So even though technically it doesn’t have קדושת שביעית
kedushat shviit and therefore should be חייב במעשר, chayav be-ma’aser, if in
reality people are accessing it and picking it and you’re not... and
it’s not a protected tree, you know, you’re not protecting the fruit,
there’s a principle by מעשר maaser. called אינו מן המשומר. eino min
ha-mishumar. So even... Even if it halachically is not הפקר, hefker, halachically
because it's a last year's tree, it's not הפקר, hefker, the reality
is during the שמיטה shmita, year people are going to treat it
as הפקר. hefker. Right. And since they're going to treat it as
הפקר, hefker, that's why there's going to be, that's why there's going
to be
no מעשר. maaser?
It's as if there were a category something like חיוב שאין אדם
יכול לעמוד בו chiyuv she-ein adam yachol la-amod bo or something like
that.
Yeah, but it's more about the nature of the fruit not being
protected. So here's the thing. I actually am jumping ahead. What I
actually explained, I think, is a simpler way of understanding it, I
mean, simpler, but you know, one status for שמיטה, shmita one status
for מעשר. maaser. The גמרא Gemara now is not looking at the
לקיטה. lekita. The גמרא Gemara, now is assuming that מעשר maaser. follows
שביעית. shviit So אביי Abaye says, I get here what you're saying,
קדושת שביעית kedushat shviit, because it grew here, therefore no מעשר. maaser
But here, in this scenario, forget לקיטה, if it has no קדושת
שביעית, kedushat shvi'it, it should have מעשר. maaser So how come you
say no מעשר? maaser? And the answer is, since people are accessing
it and picking it and it's basically, you know, you can't protect
it, then even if halachically it's not הפקר, hefker, you can't be
obligated in מעשר.
maaser Yes, yeah, I mean, it doesn't matter halachically, the notion is
you're saying if you had a whole orchard of אתרוגים... esrogim... Yes,
and you could enclose it and not allow people in it would
be...
Right, that's an interesting נפקא מינה. nafka mina. Right, if your אתרוג
tree is growing amongst other trees, you can't stop people. If you
have an orchard of אתרוג trees and you could stop people, it
would be different. And the answer is, you're right, it's not הפקר,
hefker, but it's not משומר mishumar either. It's not something that's protected.
And since in practice it's not protected, it's going to not be
חייב chayav in מעשר. maaser? But if you could protect it, it
would be different. Okay, so I'm sorry if I confused you a
little bit. I was trying to focus on the לקיטה. At this
stage, the גמרא Gemara is ignoring that and it's saying that מעשר
maaser follows שביעית. shviit So in this scenario, it's a שמיטה shmita
fruit. So since it's a שמיטה shmita, fruit, even though it's picked
in the eighth year, מעשר maaser follows and therefore
it's
פטור pattur במעשר. b'maaser.
So who does, when אביי Abaye says, אמר ליה אטו כולי עלמא
ממשמשים ביה ואת אמרת דחייב במעשר? amar lei atu kulei alma memashmshim
bei v'at amrat d'chayav b'maaser? Who's he saying that to?
No, רבא Rava. is saying that back to אביי. Abaye. רבא. Rava
רבא Rava is saying, I don't get what you're saying. Technically, it
might be not הפקר, hefker, but if everybody is accessing it, how
could you think that it should be חייב chayav in מעשר? maaser
The reason I'm saying פטור pattur במעשר b'maaser. is because in practice
you can't stop people from getting at it. Okay, all right, so
now the גמרא Gemara goes on. Let's take a look.
מיתיבי, Meisivei, I'll ask... No, I'm sorry.
Okay,
רב המנונא אמר, Rav Hamnuna amar, בת שישית שנכנסה לשביעית לעולם שישית.
bat shishit shenichnesa l'shviit le-olam shishit. It always follows
the, it always follows the שביעית shviit status. So sixth year going
into a seventh year has a full status as a sixth year
and would be a full status of a non-שמיטה, shmita which means
that it would be
חייב chayav במעשר. ובת שביעית שנכנסה לשמינית לעולם שביעית. v'bat shviit shenichnesa
l'shminit le-olam shviit. It always follows its שמיטה shmita status. So in
that case, it would be פטור במעשר. Okay, מיתיבי Meisivei says the
גמרא, I'll ask you on this: רבי שמעון בן יהודה אומר משום
רבי שמעון אתרוג בת שישית שנכנסה לשביעית, Rabbi Shimon ben Yehuda omer
mishum Rabbi Shimon esrog bat shishit shenichnesa l'shviit, the same scenario, six
going into seven, פטורה מן המעשר ופטורה מן הביעור. p'tura min ha-maaser
u-p'tura min ha-biur. It's exempt from מעשר maaser and exempt from ביעור.
bi'ur, So exempt from ביעור bi'ur we understand, it's a sixth year
fruit. Why is it exempt from
מעשר? ma'aser שאין לך דבר שחייב במעשר אלא אם כן גדל בחיוב
ונלקט
בחיוב. she-ein lecha davar she-chayav b'maaser ella im ken gadal b'chiyuv v'nilkat
b'chiyuv. So here, note, this is sort of more the direction I
was
going. Notice his language is not אטו כולי עלמא ממשמשים ביה atu
kulei alma memashmshim bei that it's פטור in מעשר ma'aser. because everybody
has access to it. It's פטור in מעשר ma'aser because it was
picked in the seventh year. And by מעשר Ma'aser, you go by
when it was picked. That was the approach I was putting out,
but that's not what we've been saying until now. Until now we've
been focusing on what is its שמיטה shmita status based on when
it blossoms. Okay, but he says it's exempt because it was picked
in the seventh year. ובת שביעית שנכנסה לשמינית, v'bat shviit shenichnesa l'shminit,
seventh year going into the eighth year, פטורה מן המעשר ופטורה מן
הביעור. p'tura min ha-maaser u-p'tura min ha-biur. It's exempt from both. Now
we guess get why it's exempt from מעשר Ma'aser because it is,
you know, well let's, because it's a שמיטה shmita fruit, right, because
it grew in the seventh. But why is it exempt from
ביעור? שאין לך דבר שחייב בביעור אלא
אם כן גדל בשביעית ונלקט בשביעית. she-ein lecha davar she-chayav b'biur ella
im ken gadal b'shviit v'nilkat b'shviit. So now what he's introducing as
opposed to this approach, which basically אביי Abaye and רבא's approach says
you go by when it blossoms and you go by שביעית Shvi'is.
and its שביעית status determines, he is saying we look at two
points: when did it blossom and when was it picked? And only
when both... both of those happen in a חיוב *chiyuv* circumstance is
it חייב chayav *chayav*. All right, I hope everybody is thoroughly confused.
So he says, the גמרא *Gemara* says like this: רישא קשיא לרב
המנונא סיפא קשיא בין לרבה בין לרב המנונא *reisha kashya le-Rav Hamnuna
seifa kashya bein le-Rabba bein le-Rav Hamnuna*. The רישא *reisha*, which has
it growing in the sixth and picked in the seventh that says
that it is going to be that it is going to be
exempt because it is picked in the seventh, that is consistent with
like, you know, רבה *Rabba*'s approach, right, which is, which says that
it's exempt when it
is in this scenario, right, in רבה *Rabba*'s case if we sort
of bracket what the logic is for a moment, right, רבה *Rabba*
says in this case, right, sixth going into the seventh, what did
רבה *Rabba* say? Sixth going into the seventh, he said it is
it is no ביעור *bi'ur* because it has no קדושת שביעית kedushat
shevi'it *kedushas shvi'is* and it says also no מעשר Ma'aser *ma'aser* because
he said, רבה *Rabba* said the reason was because יד הכל ממשמשין
*yad hakol memashmeshin*. Okay, that was what רבה *Rabba* said, right?
Everybody remember that?
Right, and רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* said, רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* said
no, it all follows שמיטה shmita, *shmita*. No ביעור *bi'ur*, so if
it's not a שמיטה shmita *shmita* fruit, yes to מעשר Ma'aser *ma'aser*,
right?
Right, because it follows its שמיטה shmita. *shmita* status. Okay, this ברייתא
*braisa* said no ביעור *bi'ur* because it's a שמיטה shmita, *shmita* fruit
and no מעשר Ma'aser. *ma'aser* because it was not for this reason
but because it was picked in the seventh year, focusing also on
when it was picked. Well, that's at least the bottom line is
consistent with רבה *Rabba*, but it contradicts רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna*. רב
המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* said yes מעשר Ma'aser *ma'aser* and this says no
מעשר Ma'aser, *ma'aser*. That's point number one of the ברייתא *braisa*. That's
the רישא *reisha* is קשיא *kashya*, so here we have a קשיא
*kashya* on רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* because רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* says
yes מעשר *ma'aser* and this says no. Now, the סיפא *seifa* says
in this case seventh going into eighth, so what do we have
in the סיפא *seifa*? רבה *Rabba* says in the סיפא *seifa* yes
ביעור *bi'ur* because it's a שמיטה shemitah *shmita* fruit and no מעשר
*ma'aser* again assuming that מעשר *ma'aser* follows שמיטה shemitah *shmita*, and רב
המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* says the same, everybody agrees here it's fully a
שמיטה Shmita *shmita* fruit. Okay, yes ביעור *bi'ur* and no מעשר *ma'aser*.
What does the ברייתא *braisa* say? This ברייתא *braisa* says because it
grew in the seventh and was picked in the eighth, it has
no ביעור *bi'ur* because the קדושת שביעית *kedushas shvi'is* requires that it
both grew in the seventh and picked in the seventh. So the
סיפא *seifa* says no ביעור *bi'ur* because it was picked in the
eighth, so that's a קשיא *kashya* both to רבה *Rabba* and to
רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna*. Okay? So, סיפא קשיא בין לרבה בין לרב
המנונא *seifa kashya bein le-Rabba bein le-Rav Hamnuna*. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says you're right, תנאי היא *tannai hi*, this whole issue is a
debate of תנאים *tannaim*, דתניא *detanya* we taught in a ברייתא *braisa*,
אמר רבי יוסי אפתומס העיד משום חמשה זקנים *amar Rabbi Yose Aphtumos
he-id mishum chamisha zekenim*, אתרוג אחר לקיטתו למעשר *esrog achar lekitaso le-ma'aser*.
You go by when it's picked for מעשר *ma'aser*. That's what we've
been saying. ורבותינו נמנו באושא ואמרו *ve-raboseinu nimnu be-Usha ve-amru*, but our
rabbis took a vote in אושא *Usha* and said, אחר לקיטתו בין
למעשר בין לשביעית *achar lekitaso bein le-ma'aser bein le-shvi'is*. No, it goes
by picking both for מעשר *ma'aser* and שביעית *shvi'is*. So the גמרא
*Gemara* says שביעית מאן דכר שמיה *shvi'is man dchar shmeih*? We haven't
been talking about שביעית *shvi'is*, like what are they arguing about? The
first opinion didn't mention שביעית *shvi'is*. So we have to interpolate and
figure out what the first opinion was saying. חסורי מחסרא והכי קתני
*chasorei mechasra ve-hachi kasani*, it's missing some words and this is what
we're saying: אתרוג אחר לקיטתו למעשר ואחר חנטתו לשביעית *esrog achar lekitaso
le-ma'aser ve-achar chanataso le-shvi'is*, and אתרוג *esrog* goes by picking for מעשר
*ma'aser* and blossoming for שביעית *shvi'is*, that's what we've been assuming. ורבותינו
נמנו באושא ואמרו *ve-raboseinu nimnu be-Usha ve-amru*, and our rabbis voted in
אושא *Usha* and said, אחר לקיטתו בין למעשר בין לשביעית *achar lekitaso
bein le-ma'aser bein le-shvi'is*. No, even for שביעית *shvi'is* you look at
the issue of picking. Which means what? That the reason here that
he said no
ביעור *bi'ur*, remember why this ברייתא *braisa* said no ביעור *bi'ur*? It
said no ביעור *bi'ur* because it was blossomed in שביעית *shvi'is* but
it was picked in the eighth and therefore no ביעור *bi'ur*. So
what does that mean? That means that even for laws of שביעית
*shvi'is* it matters when it was picked. That's the first time we're
saying that even for pure שביעית *shvi'is* laws it matters where it's
picked. So it says okay, we don't hold that way. We hold
that for שביעית *shvi'is* laws it only matters when it was blossomed.
So that gets rid of that position that says that it doesn't
have קדושת שביעית *kedushas shvi'is* because it was picked in the eighth.
For שביעית *shvi'is* that doesn't matter. Here, okay, we are basically you
know here we are going by because it does go by when
it blossomed for שביעית *shvi'is*, so here they can agree that it's
a sixth year and the whole debate about מעשר *ma'aser* was the
fact that in practice it was accessible to people and they couldn't
protect it from people. Okay, but so that's what רבה *Rabba* and
רב המנונא *Rav Hamnuna* are debating, but the fact that the ברייתא
*braisa* sort of focused overly focused on picking for שמיטה Shmita *shmita*,
that's not relevant to them, that's a different opinion.
You'd have the same problem with that rejected opinion there as well,
right? In other words the one that the one that's blossomed during
שביעית *shvi'is* and then was picked during שביעית *shvi'is* while it was
still growing during שמיטה Shmita *shmita* it would not be הפקר hefker.
*hefker* because it's no ביעור *bi'ur*, right?
You'd have the same problem in יד הכל בו *yad hakol bo*.
Right. But here it is actually has קדושת שביעית.
The one that you just crossed out, there's no ביעור, right? There's
no ביעור that means it's not הפקר. So you'd have to protect
it also, it'd have to be משומר. meshumar. You
have the same problem.
I can't process that right now. Okay, fine. Anyways, the רמב"ם Rambam
says like this. Okay, איתמר Itmar was taught, רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש
Rabbi Yochanan veResh Lakish both say, אתרוג בשישית שנכנסה לשביעית לעולם שישית.
etrog bashishit shenichnesa lishvi'it l'olam shishit.
So again, not like רבה, they say once it blossomed in the
sixth year, it has קדושת שביעית, for שמיטה Shmita, הלכות halachot it's
the sixth year, it's a full sixth year status, even presumably for
the מעשר that follows. כי אתא רבין אמר רבי יוחנן, Ki ata
Ravin amar Rabbi Yochanan, when רבין Ravin came from ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, אתרוג בת שישית
שנכנסה לשביעית, etrog bat shishit shenichnesa lishvi'it, if it's sixth year going
into seventh, אפילו כזית, afilu kezayit, even if in the sixth year
it was only a tiny size, the size of an olive, ונעשה
ככר, venasa kikar, and by the time it was the seventh year
it had grown to the size of like a loaf,
nevertheless, חייבין עליה משום טבל, chayavin aleha mishum tevel, it has the
obligations of מעשר. So again, in this case, right, since here, even
if it was a tiny little little olive size here, and then
it became huge during שמיטה, Shmita nevertheless, you say, ah, it's gotta
be a שמיטה fruit, like look at it, the whole thing grew
during שמיטה. No, if it blossomed before ט"ו בשבט, Tu B'shvat it's
a sixth year, and once it's the sixth year for שמיטה, we
assume that מעשר is going to follow as a result and therefore
it's going to be חייב and it's going to be טבל. tevel.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. Okay. אילן שחנטו, Ilan shechanto,
we're almost done, פירותיו קודם ט"ו בשבט מתעשר לשנה שעברה. peirotav kodem
Tu B'shvat mitaser leshana she'avra. If it blossomed before ט"ו בשבט, Tu
B'shvat, now we're no longer talking about an אתרוג, thank God. We're
talking about a normal tree which goes by blossom. If it blossomed
before ט"ו בשבט, Tu BiShvat it goes for the previous year. אחר
ט"ו בשבט מתעשר לשנה הבאה. Achar Tu B'shvat mitaser leshana haba'a. After
ט"ו בשבט, Tu BiShvat. the follow year, or really it means the
current year. אמר רבי נחמיה, Amar Rabbi Nechemia, במה דברים אמורים, bameh
devarim amorim, when is this true? באילן שעושה שתי בריכות בשנה, B'ilan
she'oseh shtei breichot beshana, if it has two... a בריכה breicha
is really a word used by pigeons, which means like a... what's
it called when you have a cluster, when pigeons like lay a
clutch? Right, is that the word, a clutch of of pigeons or
something? Some say it's brood. A brood. Okay, so it's a word
borrowed from pigeons when they lay a when they like lay a
bunch of eggs. So it's so when is it true? When they
have two layings in a year. Okay? So the גמרא says, שתי
בריכות סלקא דעתך? shtei breichot salka daitach? What do you mean two
layings? It's a tree, it's not a pigeon. אלא אימא כעין שתי
בריכות, Ela eima k'ein shtei breichot, like two layings, meaning when it
gives forth fruit twice in a year. אבל אילן העושה בריכה אחת,
Aval ilan ha'oseh breicha achat,
but a tree that only produces fruit at one time in the
year, כגון דקלים, kegon dekalim, like palm trees, וזיתים, vezetim, and olives,
וחרובים, vecharuvim, and carobs, אף על פי שחנטו פירותיהם קודם ט"ו בשבט,
af al pi shechanto peiroteihem kodem Tu B'shvat, even if it was
before ט"ו בשבט, Tu BiShvat, מתעשרין לשנה הבאה, mitasrin leshana haba'a, they
are this year's fruit, not next year's fruit. Now this is a
radical reshape and I will tell you, come on, so everything has
been emphasize אתרוג because it has been confusing the heck out of
us between whether it's blossoming or picking, but at least the one
thing we had clear was trees go by ט"ו בשבט. Tu B'Shvat,
Now he is coming and confusing it all and he's saying, look,
and this should remind you of the discussion about legumes and the
idea of making the dates based on convenience rather than on some
logic, because he says like this, he says, remember by legumes, we
said it really should go by when you picked, but they're picked
at all different times, so we want to make a fixed time
so we go by when it takes root. He seems to be
saying the same thing by trees and he's saying, it really should
go by when it's picked. So if you have a tree that
really only all ripens at the same time and is picked at
once, we're going to go by when it's picked. When have we
been saying ט"ו בשבט? That's because trees they blossom at, you know,
because trees that have that have fruit at multiple times in the
year, so there, because the times when it's picked will be over
multiple times, we want to pick a time that's more single and
centralized, fixed, so we'll go by blossoming. Okay, that sort of seems
to be his his logic here. But, you know, the problem is
that he doesn't switch between the issue of picked versus blossomed, he's
switched between the issue of ט"ו בשבט and ראש השנה, but I
assume that it is something that is similar in the sense of
that in the sense of what do you call it, in the
sense of what happens, let me erase all of this, what happens
at that
time. So
if you've got a tree, again, I'm just using
the example of the legumes as another case where we changed things
in order to get a fixed time.
So by the legumes because it was over multiple times it was
picked we want to focus in on השרשה.
By the trees what he's saying is, if you've got a case,
here's ראש השנה and here's
ט"ו בשבט,
okay, and most trees let's say blossom around here, that seems to
be the assumption why we. So that and let's say though they're
picked at multiple times, here I keep on doing picked, it's not
picked, it's blossoming, okay? They it says but
it says the reason I'm saying it is because he says גמר
פרי gmar pri. that it finishes, right? It has, you know, when
is it producing? It's got like גמר פרי gmar pri. here, and
then you've got another גמר פרי gmar pri. here, right? If it
has multiple times of where the fruits ripen, right, that's שתי בריכות
בשנה, shtei breichot bashanah, ripens multiple times, so you don't want to
go by גמר פרי. gmar pri. Or actually you don't want to
go by...
oh, I'm confusing myself.
If you go by ראש השנה and you focus... well I guess
it's both. If you go by ראש השנה and you focus on
the גמר פרי, gmar pri it's going to be all over the
place. So what you rather do is you focus on the blossoming
and you focus on ט"ו בשבט which makes it into a single
time. But if it's something that has only
one... בריכה בשנה, breichah bashanah, I'm totally confusing myself.
Is this the other way around?
No, hold on. I can't understand how this makes sense unless it's
both going by ראש השנה and going by גמר פרי. gmar pri.
One minute.
Hold on.
No, I think I am saying it right. One minute.
Yeah, no I am
right. אע"פ שחנטו פירותיהם קודם ט"ו בשבט מתעשרין לשנה הבאה,
Af al pi shechanutu peiroteihem
kodem Tu BiShvat mitasrin l'shanah haba'ah, which means, one minute...
yeah, I think Rashi is implying that you would go by גמר
פרי. gmar pri, One minute.
Yeah, Rashi is implying that you would go by גמר פרי. gmar
pri. Okay, I'm going to assume that without, okay. Right,
right, right.
ט"ו בשבט כהתחלה לשנה
שבאה.
Tu BiShvat k'hatchalah
l'shanah sheba'ah.
Right, I don't think he's saying ראש השנה. He is saying, I'm
sorry, I'm sorry if I'm confusing everybody. He is saying you go
by גמר פרי. Gmar pri, Okay, let's try this again, okay? So
here, here's the way it's saying is that normally if it has
multiple times in which the trees are finishing, you've got גמר פרי
Gmar pri multiple times throughout the year, right, two or more, then
you're not going to want to focus on גמר פרי. You're going
to want to focus on a fixed time, which is blossoming, which
is ט"ו בשבט. And therefore it would go by that.
But if it only blossoms once...
presumably it only
blossoms
once. But if it
only has one type of גמר פרי, I'm totally confusing myself. Is
this
the
other way around? No, hold on. But if
it only has one time when it finishes, when it's picked and
when it ripens, then we're only going... then we're not going to
focus on the blossoming and we're going to focus on the גמר
פרי. So even though it blossomed before ט"ו בשבט, מתעשרין לשנה הבאה.
mitasrin l'shanah haba'ah. Okay,
is that finally a little... I'm sorry for the confusion, but is
everybody more or less clear? If there's multiple times it finishes, we
don't want to focus on when it finishes, we want to focus
on when it blossoms. But if it only finishes once, if it
only has one sort of produce in the year, we're going to
focus on the produce and not on the blossoming.
שתי בריכות Shtei breichot would mean בריכות הרבה breichot harbeh or בריכה
ממושכת. breichah memushechet.
Yeah, not limited to two. Right.
Okay, so let's take a look. אמר רב יוחנן נהגו עם בחרובין
כרבי נחמיה. Amar Rav Yochanan nahagu am becharuvin k'Rabbi Nechemia. The people
practiced by חרובין charuvin like רבי נחמיה, Rabbi Nechemia, and they didn't
go by when it blossomed, they go by... they went by when
it... since that only had one ripening of the fruit, one... then
they went by the ripening, not by when it blossomed. Okay, again
this indicates by the way that trees are rabbinic. If we can
play around like this and shift between blossoming and finishing, obviously it's
going to be because we have total latitude here because it's rabbinic.
איתיביה ריש לקיש לרבי יוחנן. Eitiveih Reish Lakish l'Rabbi Yochanan. So ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish asked רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. בנות שוח, Bnot shuach,
which is a certain type of
a... how do they just translate בנות שוח bnot shuach over there?
White figs. White figs, thank you. שביעית שלהן שנייה מפני שעושות לשלש
שנים. Shevi'it shelahen shniyah mipnei sheosot l'shalosh shanim. So their שמיטה is
in the second year because it takes three years for them to
ripen. Okay, which means that you have a... here, you've got... here
it is
a שמיטה year, okay, and it's going to take two years to
ripen, so way here you're going to be in year number two
and picking these figs, and they're going to have קדושת שביעית because
it took them three years to ripen. What does that show you?
It shows... It shows you that you go by blossoming, not that
you go by picking, okay? And presumably this is one of those
things that has only, that doesn't have multiple multiple,
you know, multiple times, and nevertheless, you're going by blossoming, you're not
going by picking. So he says, אשתיק, Ishtik, he was silent, he
didn't have a response. You're right, according to his logic it shouldn't
have gone by blossoming, it should have gone by picking, by the
finished fruit. אמאי רבי אבא הכהן ברבי יוסי הכהן, Amai Rabbi Abba
Ha-Kohen ברבי Rabbi Yose Ha-Kohen, אמאי אשתיק, amai ishtik, why was he
silent? לימא ליה, Lema lei, why doesn't he say back to him,
אמינא לך אנא רבי נחמיה, Amina lach ana Rabbi Nechemia, ואת אמרת
לי רבנן? ve-at amret li Rabbanan? No, I told you this was
the position of רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemia. So you're telling me that
there's a rabbinic position against it? So what? That's not a question
to me. I'm still telling you the רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia position.
So he says,
דאמר ליה, D'amar lei, because no, because the response that could be,
שבקת רבנן ועבדת כרבי נחמיה? Shavket Rabbanan ve-avdet k'Rabbi Nechemia? How are
you entitled to leave a larger position of the rabbis, that's the
more majority position, and go by this רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia idea
that says that if it only has one product, not multiple, you
know, not multiple products, that you go by when it's finished? What
allows you to do that? If the majority position is you always
go by when it blossoms. So he says, לימא ליה, Lema lei,
why doesn't he say back to him, look, כי אמינא לך אנא
נהגו, Ki amina lach ana nahagu, I didn't say the הלכה Halacha
was רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemia. I said the people practiced like רבי
נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemia. ואת אמרת לי איסורא, Ve-at amret li issura, and
you're telling me, oh, oh, but halachically we go by the rabbis.
I agree we go by the rabbis that you go by חנטה.
I was just telling you that there's a common practice out there,
not that it's the הלכה, Halacha, but that there's a common practice
to go by רבי נחמיה. Rabbi Nechemia. So
דאמר
ליה, D'amar lei, because he would say back to him, במקום איסורא
כי נהגו שבקינן להו? Be-makom issura ki nahagu shavkinan lehu?
I don't get it. If halachically the real הלכה Halacha is you
go by when it blossoms, how could you just casually say, 'Oh
yeah, but the people are going like רבי נחמיה Rabbi Nechemia and
they're going by when it ripens'? How could you allow that? If
there's a real הלכה Halacha that it goes by when it blossoms,
you shouldn't just casually mention that the practice is in violation of
it. So לימא ליה, Lema lei, why didn't he say back to
him, look, כי אמינא לך אנא, Ki amina lach ana, now we
get to this issue of רבנן Rabbanan or דאורייתא. De-Oraisa. When was
I saying it to you? מעשר חרובין, Ma'aser charuvin, דרבנן. De-rabbanan. I
was talking about מעשר, מעשר by trees is rabbinic. So since מעשר
by trees is rabbinic, we can be a little bit more flexible,
and therefore we can sometimes go by גמר פרי, sometimes go by
חנטה. That's why ואת אמרת לי שביעית דאורייתא. ve-at amret li Shvi'is
De-Oraisa. Your example of when שמיטה applies, שמיטה by trees is biblical.
מעשר by trees is rabbinic, but שמיטה by trees is biblical. So
by שמיטה, of course we would go by חנטה. My whole idea
that we would go by גמר פרי was when it was rabbinic,
when it was about מעשר. אלא אמר רבי אבא הכהן, Ella amar
Rabbi Abba Ha-Kohen, so רבי אבא Rabbi Abba is going to say,
תמהי אם השיב ריש לקיש תשובה זו. Temahi im heishiv Resh Lakish
teshuvah zo. I'm astounded if ריש לקיש Resh Lakish challenged רבי יוחנן.
Rabbi Yochanan. So the גמרא says, אם השיב? Im heishiv? What do
you mean if he challenged רבי יוחנן? Rabbi Yochanan? הא אותיב, Ha
osiv, he did challenge רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. The problem was that
רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was silent, didn't respond. אלא אימא, Ella eima,
so what I mean to say is, אם קיבלה רבי יוחנן או
לא קיבלה. Im kibla Rabbi Yochanan oh lo kibla. Just because רבי
יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was silent doesn't mean that he didn't have a
response. Sometimes you're silent because you don't think that it was a
decent question. So רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan was saying his idea about
מעשר and he was challenging him on שביעית. He didn't bother to
respond. Okay, so we got a little bit confused at the end,
but just to summarize, we've seen a lot. We've seen that trees
go by blossoming and by טו בשבט, but we've challenged it in
two ways. First of all, we said that by אתרוג sometimes it
goes by picking, and what we've also said is that by trees
that finish only once in a year, maybe they don't go by
blossoming, maybe they actually go by when they finish. That anyway besides
the issues of would that matter whether it's שמיטה or מעשר, what's
דרבנן, De-rabbanan, what's דאורייתא. De-Oraisa. So just so that we ended on
a nice confusion.